Puebla, Mexico records 1655-1898 (bulk 1840-1898)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Puebla, Mexico records, 1655-1898 (bulk 1840-1898)
MS 004
Puebla (Mexico: State)
Civil and military records of the City, State and National governments, as well as Catholic Church records. Included are wills, deeds, property records, correspondence, government decrees, civil pensions, military battalion records, convent and monastery records, and fund administration records.
1.7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The state of Puebla is in the central southeastern part of Mexico; its capital is the city of Puebla. Some of the documents have "Puebla de los Angeles," which was the original name when founded by the Spanish in 1532. During the mid-nineteenth century, it was occupied by American, and later French, forces.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Civil and Church Records
Series II: Military Records
Scope and Content Note
Civil and military records of the City, State and National governments, as well as Catholic Church records. Included are wills, deeds, property records, correspondence, government decrees, civil pensions, military battalion records, convent and monastery records, and fund administration records. Most are manuscript, but some are printed, particularly the government decrees, which date from 1856-1892. Accounts and documents are present for Casa del Santuario de la Madre Santisima de la Luz, 1838-1839; Colegio de Ni{228}nas Virgenes, 1798-1804; Colegio de Nuestra Se{228}nora de los Gozos, 1835; Convent de San Antonio, 1834, 1855; Convent de San Francisco y Curato de Huejotsingo, 1856; Convent de Santa Barbara, 1694, 1747, 1808-1809; and Convent de Santa Catalina, 1841-1842, 1857. Wills and estate documents, 1686-1858; property deeds and titles, 1857; and sale documents, 1655-1895, mostly involve property left to the church. Personal letters date from as early as the 1680s and 1690s. A substantial group of documents from 1756 to 1853 relates to pious works, donations and foundations. Military records are chiefly retirement papers, an 1818 muster roll of the Royal Bn. of Puebla, and records of the 4th Bn. Casadores, Tehuacan, from 1867.
Collection is in Spanish.
Access Terms
Mexico -- Ejercito -- Documents
Colegio de Ninas Virgenes (Puebla, Mexico)
Colegio de Nuestra Senora de los Gozos (Puebla, Mexico)
Convento de San Antonio (Puebla, Mexico)
Convento de San Francisco y Curato de Huejotsingo (Mexico)
Convento de Santa Barbara (Puebla, Mexico)
Convento de Santa Catalina (Puebla, Mexico)
Convento de Santa Catalina (Puebla, Mexico)
Casa del Santuario de la Madre Santisima de la Luz (Puebla, Mexico
Catholic Church -- Mexico -- Puebla (State) -- Records and correspondence
Military pensions -- Mexico -- Puebla (State)
Church property -- Mexico -- Puebla (State)
Puebla (Mexico: State) -- History -- Sources
Puebla (Mexico) -- History -- Sources
Correspondence
Wills
Decrees
Accounts
Container List
- Series I: Civil and Church Records, 1655-1892
  - Boarding-house Accounts, Puebla. 1844-1846 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Pertaining to the managment of the house at no.6, Camarin St., Puebla.
  - Casa del Santuario de la Madre Santisima de la Luz, Puebla. 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Account book. Contains also a record of some deaths.
  - Census, Instructions for. Tlaxcala. 1883 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Pertaining to the collection of statistical data for the federal government. Issued by Pacheco, Sec. of State.
  - Chaplaincies, Puebla. 1789-1850 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1789. Certification of official records for official purposes.
    1845. Request for a chaplaincy by Don Jose J. Vivenos, proxy for Col. Don Manuel Gomez. (2 copies)
    1850. Letters from the office of the vicar-general of Puebla to the Treasurer (?) of the chaplains' funds, directing the transfer of funds between certain chaplaincies.
  - Church Records, Miscellaneous. 1674-1847 (1, 5)
    Circular issued by the Bishop of Chiapas concerning church property, prescribing measures to be taken by church personnel in the face of persecution. Puebla de los Angeles, December 24, 1847.
    Miscellaneous church records sewn together as a single volume. Includes information on sale of houses and the administration of pious works. Puebla. 1732-1808.
  - Church Records: Petition to Spanish King. 1799 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Colegio de Ninas Virgenes, Puebla. 1798-1804 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Accounts and documents.
  - Colegio de Nuestra Senora de los Gozos, Puebla. 1835 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Convent de San Antonio, Puebla. 1834-1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Convent de San Francisco y Curato de Huejotsingo, Huejotsingo. 1856 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Convent de Santa Barbara, Puebla. 1694, 1747, 1808-1809 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Convent de Santa Catalina, Puebla. 1841-1857 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Decrees, Government. 1856-1892 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
  - Letters, Miscellaneous (Official). 1862-1885 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1862. Letters of Military Commander of Tlaxcala to the Secretary of the Treasury, appointing a prefect of the district of Tlaxcala because of illness of the present incumbent.
    1862. Letter of Military Commander of Tlaxcala requesting Secretary of the Treasury of Tlaxcala to submit a normal tax report showing those citizens who are behind in payments.
    1865. Letter from Postmaster General of Puebla to Postmaster General of San Martin, enclosing 83 pesos in stamps, with attached invoice.
    1884-1885. Receipts for 16.00 pesos received from head of Treasury Dept., Puebla, in the case of C. Carlos Rubio, fined by court sentence.
  - Letters, Miscellaneious (Personal). 1683-1884 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Varous subjects and places. (approx. 12)
  - Franciscans. 1792 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Information concerning royal provisions freeing the Franciscans, their works, and properties from taxes. Puebla.
  - Estate of Captain Juan Sanchez Oredon. 1686, 1693 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Documents pertaining to an estate left to a convent. Puebla.
  - Pensions, Civil. Treasury Office, Puebla. 1856 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pious Works, Donations, Foundations. 1756-1853 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Varous documents. (approx. 16, some of great length)
  - Property, (Claims) Puebla. 1857, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Property, (Deeds and Titles). 1857 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Property, (Sales). 1655-1857 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Property, (Sale of land to Manuel Armijo). 1880-1895 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Water Lease, Puebla. 1839 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Copy of original lease for the use of overflow water from the spring located below the Church of the 3d Order of San Franciso, Puebla.
  - Wills. 1761-1858 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    16 wills, some providing for the establishment of pious funds at various churches and convents; donations for special masses, and the disposition of property to the Church.
- Series II: Military Records. 1818-1898
  - Army Station List. October 1898 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Awards, Military. 1823, 1842 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Documents of Josefa Bermudes de Rodriguez. 1863 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Various documents of the wife of Juan Ignacio Rodriguez, dealing with his military service. Included is a certificate of his death and burial.
  - 4th Bn. Casadores, Tehuacan. 1867 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Deserters, November.
    Hospital Guard Reports, October-November.
    Mess Bills, September-November.
    Special Reports of the Guard, October 1-November 4.
    Supply Room "Issues," November.
    Supply Room "Turn-ins," November.
    Report of Prisoners delivered by the old Officer of the Day to the new Officer of the Day, November.
    Sgt. of the Guard Reports, November.
  - Miscellaneious Military Letters. 1822-1867 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    1822. Letter certifying payment to Lt. Fernando Astonga.
    1852. Acknowledgement of receipt for pension, by Maria Susana Matamoros.
    1867. Letter from a soldier in prison to his captain, requesting help in his case.
    Letter from Genario Rodriguez, Lt. Col., 1st Light Battalion, to the commander of the Military District of Tenpan, declaring his loyality to the national government and requesting permisssion to unite his battalion with the forces of the General-in-Chief, Ignacio R. Matorri, who is in the north beyond friendly lines. Puebla.
  - Pensions, Military. 1851-1856 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Royal Bn. of Puebla, Muster Roll. August 3, 1818 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Treasury, Puebla, Retired Military Personnel. 1856 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Military Retired List, Puebla. June 1833 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Retirement Papers, A - C. (These are the Retirement Papers of individuals whose names appear on the list in Folder #9, arranged alphabetically according to first name of individual). No Date (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Retirement Papers, D - I. (These are the Retirement Papers of individuals whose names appear on the list in Folder #9, arranged alphabetically according to first name of individual). No Date (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Retirement Papers, J. (These are the Retirement Papers of individuals whose names appear on the list in Folder #9, arranged alphabetically according to first name of individual). No Date (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Retirement Papers, L - M. (These are the Retirement Papers of individuals whose names appear on the list in Folder #9, arranged alphabetically according to first name of individual). No Date (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Retirement Papers, N - Z. (These are the Retirement Papers of individuals whose names appear on the list in Folder #9, arranged alphabetically according to first name of individual). No Date (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Retirement Papers. (not on list in Folder #9, Box 3). No Date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Retirement Papers (miscellaneous and incomplete). No Date (Box 4, Folder 6)